Guide to the Haymarket Affair Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Haymarket Affair collection
1872-1901
GEN MSS 516
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.05
(8 boxes) + 2 broadside folders, 1 art storage item
The bulk of the collection consists of the papers of Illinois State's Attorney Julius S. Grinnell, who led the prosecution in the Haymarket trial in 1886-1887. These include trial evidence, notes and drafts of legal briefs, personal papers, and printed ephemera. The collection also includes a few items that were added to Grinnell's papers in the 1950s-60s by collector Frederick B. Adams. Trial evidence is chiefly in German, and consists of manuscripts, correspondence, leaflets, and other items seized from the offices of the Arbeiter-Zeitung, a publication of the International Working People's Association, with which many of the defendants were involved. The manuscripts are chiefly holograph drafts of editorials by August Spies and Michael Schwab; much of the correspondence is to Spies, including several letters from Johann Most, editor of the New York paper Die Freiheit. The evidence also includes other socialist and anarchist newspapers, as well as fragments of the bomb that exploded in Haymarket Square. Papers of the State's Attorney's Office include Grinnell's notes and drafts of legal briefs prepared for the trial and for the defense's appeal to the Illinois Supreme Court in 1887. These include a draft letter from a police spy to Lucy Parsons, Albert Parsons's wife. Also present are personal papers of Grinnell: most relate directly to the trial while others document his later career. The collection also contains printed ephemera of the socialist and anarchist movements, including a number of items relating specifically to the Haymarket affair. Among these are cabinet card photographs of six of the eight convicted men.
Grinnell, Julius S. (Julius Sprague), 1842-1898
Schwab, Michael, 1853-
Spies, August Vincent Theodore, 1855-1887
Adams, Frederick B. (Frederick Baldwin), 1910-2001
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Hans P. Kraus, 1987.
Custodial History
This collection was acquired by H. P. Kraus from Frederick B. Adams, Jr. (Yale 1932) in 1969. Adams acquired the papers of Julius S. Grinnell in 1952, and later added a few other Haymarket-related items to the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile Materials in box 8 may be consulted only with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies or photographic prints for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
HAYMARKET CHRONOLOGY
Numerous secondary sources about the Haymarket affair exist, including two full-length monographs, and these should be consulted for a detailed history of the events documented by these papers. The chronology below is a brief summary of the events surrounding the trial.
1886 May 1: Beginning of a general strike by Chicago laborers for the eight-hour day.
1886 May 3: Police kill several striking workers during a confrontation at McCormick Reaper Works factory in Chicago.
1886 May 4: A meeting in Chicago's Haymarket Square, held to protest police violence at McCormick's, is broken up by police. A bomb is thrown into the ranks of police by an unidentified person. The police open fire on the gathering; the crowd fires back. Seven officers are fatally wounded by the bomb or by bullets; an unknown number of meeting attendees are killed and wounded.
1886 May 5 and following: Suspects are arrested, including leaders and members of local groups of the International Working People's Association (IWPA), the Central Labor Union, Lehr- und Wehr-verein, and other Chicago socialist and anarchist organizations. Particularly targeted are those associated with IWPA-sponsored publications The Alarm, the Arbeiter-Zeitung, Vorbote, and Die Fackel, all published from the same office at 107 Fifth Avenue. Papers, weapons, and other materials are seized without warrant from suspects' homes and offices by police, State's Attorney Julius S. Grinnell, and Assistant State's Attorneys Edmund Furthmann and Francis W. Walker. Special counsel George C. Ingham joins the prosecution as they prepare the case for the State. The Central Labor Union retains the legal firm of Moses Salomon and Sigmund Zeisler, along with attorneys William A. Foster and Captain William P. Black, to represent the accused.
1886 May 27: A Grand Jury indicts ten suspects for the murder of Officer Mathias J. Degan: August Spies and Michael Schwab, editors of the Arbeiter-Zeitung; Albert R. Parsons, editor of The Alarm; Adolph Fischer, a typesetter at the Arbeiter-Zeitung and editor of a non-IWPA paper, Der Anarchist; George Engel, co-editor of Der Anarchist; Samuel Fielden, a leader in the American Group of the IWPA; Louis Lingg and Oscar Neebe, organizers with the Central Labor Union; William Seliger, secretary of the Carpenter's Union, with whom Lingg boards; and Rudolph Schnaubelt, brother-in-law of Michael Schwab and active member of the IWPA. Parsons and Schnaubelt have earlier fled the city to avoid arrest; Seliger turns state's evidence.
1886 Jun 5: Spies, Schwab, Fischer, Engel, Fielden, Lingg, and Neebe are arraigned, pleading not guilty.
1886 Jun 10: Trial set to begin June 21 in the Cook County Criminal Court, under Judge Joseph E. Gary.
1886 Jun 21: Defense motions to quash the indictment. The motion is overruled. Spies, Schwab, Fielden, and Neebe motion for a separate trial from Fischer, Engel, and Lingg. The motion is overruled. Parsons returns to Chicago and surrenders himself in court, pleading not guilty. Jury selection begins.
1886 Jul 15: Last juror sworn. Opening arguments.
1886 Jul 16-Aug 11: Witness testimony and introduction of evidence.
1886 Aug 20: Jury delivers verdict of guilty for all eight defendants. Defense motions for a new trial.
1886 Oct 1: Arguments on motion for new trial begin.
1886 Oct 7: Motion for new trial denied.
1886 Oct 7-9: Speeches by the accused to the court.
1886 Oct 9: Judge Gary pronounces sentences: Neebe is sentenced to fifteen years hard labor; Spies, Parsons, Schwab, Fielden, Engel, Lingg, and Fischer to execution by hanging on December 3.
1886 Oct 28-Nov 13: Defense files bills of exception, appealing to Illinois Supreme Court for a writ of error.
1886 Nov 25: Illinois Supreme Court grants defendants a stay of execution and writ of error.
1887 March 17-19: Appeal is argued before Illinois Supreme Court. Leonard Swett joins Black and Salomon & Zeisler in representing the eight anarchists; Illinois Attorney General George Hunt joins Grinnell and Ingham in arguing for the State.
1887 Sep 14: Illinois Supreme Court upholds ruling of lower court.
1887 Oct 27: Defense appeals to U. S. Supreme Court.
1887 Nov 2: U. S. Supreme Court rules the case out of Federal jurisdiction.
1887 Nov 10: Lingg commits suicide in his cell. Governor Richard Oglesby commutes sentences of Schwab and Fielden, who have petitioned for clemency, to life imprisonment.
1887 Nov 11: Spies, Parsons, Fischer, and Engel are hanged.
1893 Jun 26: Governor John P. Altgeld pardons Schwab, Fielden, and Neebe, for the reasons that they did not receive a fair trial and were never proven guilty of murdering Officer Degan.
JULIUS S. GRINNELL
Julius Sprague Grinnell was born in Massena, New York, on November 13, 1842. He was educated at Potsdam and Lawrenceville Academies, and graduated from Middlebury College in 1866. After college he taught at or was principal of the academy in Ogdensburg, New York, while he studied law with local attorneys. He was admitted to practice in New York State in 1868.
According to contemporary newspaper accounts of his career, Grinnell married in 1869 and moved to Chicago in 1870, where he practiced law privately until he was elected City Attorney in 1879. He was elected State's Attorney in 1884.
In 1887, in addition to the Haymarket case, Grinnell also prosecuted a high-profile case against corrupt city officials. On the strength of these two prosecutions, he was elected Judge of the Circuit Court of Cook County, Illinois, in June of that year, and began his term in December.
For financial reasons, Judge Grinnell retired into private practice in 1891, accepting an offer to serve as counsel for the City Railway Company. He died of a heart attack on June 8, 1898, in Chicago.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the collection consists of the papers of Illinois State's Attorney Julius S. Grinnell, who led the prosecution in the Haymarket trial in 1886-1887. These include trial evidence, notes and drafts of legal briefs, personal papers, and printed ephemera. The collection also includes a few items that were added to Grinnell's papers in the 1950s-60s by collector Frederick B. Adams. Trial evidence is chiefly in German, and consists of manuscripts, correspondence, leaflets, and other items seized from the offices of the Arbeiter-Zeitung, a publication of the International Working People's Association, with which many of the defendants were involved. The manuscripts are chiefly holograph drafts of editorials by August Spies and Michael Schwab; much of the correspondence is to Spies, including several letters from Johann Most, editor of the New York paper Die Freiheit. The evidence also includes other socialist and anarchist newspapers, as well as fragments of the bomb that exploded in Haymarket Square. Papers of the State's Attorney's Office include Grinnell's notes and drafts of legal briefs prepared for the trial and for the defense's appeal to the Illinois Supreme Court in 1887. These include a draft letter from a police spy to Lucy Parsons, Albert Parsons's wife. Also present are personal papers of Grinnell: most relate directly to the trial while others document his later career. The collection also contains printed ephemera of the socialist and anarchist movements, including a number of items relating specifically to the Haymarket affair. Among these are cabinet card photographs of six of the eight convicted men.
Throughout the collection are manuscript notes written by the collector and previous custodian of the papers Frederick B. Adams, and many typed descriptions and English translations which were likely prepared by Adams. These have been left with the items they describe, and their presence noted where they occur.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Haymarket Trial Evidence. II. Papers of the State's Attorney's Office. III. Personal Papers of Julius S. Grinnell. IV. Printed Ephemera; V. Other Papers.
Appendix: Kebabian Catalog Cross Reference
The arrangement of this collection differs considerably from that described in the catalog of the collection prepared for H. P. Kraus (Kebabian, John S., The Haymarket Affair and the Trial of the Chicago Anarchists: Original Manuscripts, Letters, Articles and Printed Material of the Anarchists and of the State Prosecutor, Julius S. Grinnell. New York: H. P. Kraus, 1970).
The index below provides a cross reference from the Kebabian catalog number, noted as K-#, to the current location of the same material in the present arrangement.
K-1: Box 5, folder 87
K-2: Box 5, folder 81
K-3: Box 5, folder 81
K-4: Box 5, folder 91
K-5: Box 2, folder 31
K-6: Box 2, folder 39
K-7: Box 2, folder 37
K-8: Box 2, folder 38
K-9: Box 2, folder 40
K-10: Box 5, folder 92
K-11: Box 2, folder 34
K-12: Box 2, folder 33
K-13: Box 2, folder 35
K-14: Box 2, folder 32
K-15: Box 6, folder 110
K-16: Box 2, folder 41
K-17: Box 2, folder 42
K-18: Box 2, folder 43
K-19: Box 2, folder 52
K-20: Box 2, folder 44
K-21: Box 2, folder 36
K-22: Box 1, folder 4
K-23: Box 2, folder 53
K-24: Box 1, folder 14
K-25: Box 6, folder 108
K-26: Box 6, folder 111
K-27: Box 2, folder 45
K-28: Box 5, folder 93
K-29: Box 6, folder 107
K-30: Box 2, folder 50
K-31: Box 2, folder 46
K-32: Box 2, folder 25
K-33: Box 6, folder 112
K-34: Box 1, folder 8
K-35: Box 1, folder 9
K-36: Box 2, folder 47
K-37: Box 5, folder 94
K-38: Box 1, folder 5 (top half of p. 13)
------Box 1, folder 6 (pp. 3-8)
------Box 1, folder 10
------Box 2, folders 15-17
------Box 2, folder 20
------Box 2, folders 22-24
------Box 2, folders 26-29
------Box 2, folder 54
------Box 3, folder 58
K-39: Box 1, folder 11 (second fragment of p. 10)
K-40: Box bsd, folder 109
------Box 2, folder 21
K-41: Box 2, folder 49
K-42: Box 1, folder 7
K-43: Box 2, folder 18
K-44: Box 6, folder 106
K-45: Box 1, folder 6 (p. 1 - top half of p. 2)
K-46: Box 1, folder 11
K-47: Box 1, folder 5
------Box 1, folder 13
K-48: Box 1, folder 7 (p. 4)
------Box 2, folder 19
K-49: Box 1, folder 6 (bottom half of p. 2)
K-50: Box 1, folder 12
K-51: Box 1, folder 3
K-52: Box 1, folder 1
K-53: Box 1, folder 2
K-54: Box 2, folder 30
K-55: Box 2, folder 51
K-56: Box 6, folder 113
K-57: Box 3, folder 56
K-58: Box 3, folder 57
K-59: Box bsd, folder 114
K-60: Box 3, folder 60
K-61: Box 6, folder 115
K-62: Box 6, folder 115
K-63: Box 6, folder 116
K-64: Box 3, folder 69
K-65: Box 3, folder 61
K-66: Box 3, folder 65
K-67: Box 3, folder 67
K-68: Box 3, folder 68
K-69: Box 3, folder 62
K-70: Box 3, folder 64
K-71: Box 5, folder 96
K-72: Box 3, folders 71-73
K-73: Box 3, folder 75
K-74: Box 3, folder 70
K-75: Box 3, folder 74
K-76: Box 3, folder 78
K-77: Box 3, folder 77
K-78: Box 5, folder 104
K-79: Box 5, folder 95
K-80: Box 3, folder 59
K-81: Box 5, folder 97
K-81A: Box 5, folder 105
K-82: Box 4, folder 79
K-83: Box 4, folder 80
K-84: Box 6, folder 117
K-85: Box 6, folder 121
K-86: Box 5, folder 98
K-87: Box 6, folder 118
K-88: Box 5, folder 101
K-89: Box 5, folder 85
K-90: Box 4, folder 99
K-91: Box 5, folder 100
K-92: Box 5, folder 102
K-93: Box 5, folder 84
K-94: Box 5, folder 82
K-95: Box 5, folder 83
K-96: Box 5, folders 88-90
K-97: Box 6, folder 119
K-98: Box 5, folder 103
K-99: Box 5, folder 86
K-100: Box 2, folder 48
K-101: artstor, folder 120
Arbeiter-Zeitung (Chicago, Ill.); Anarchism -- Periodicals; Anarchism -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Anarchists -- Portraits; Anarchists -- United States -- 19th century; Bombings -- United States -- 19th century; Haymarket Square Riot, Chicago, Ill., 1886; Journalism, Socialist -- United States -- 19th century; Labor movement -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Labor unions -- Illinois -- Chicago -- 19th century; Newspapers -- Illinois -- 19th century; Press, Anarchist -- United States -- 19th century; Socialism -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Trials (Anarchy) -- United States -- 19th century; Chicago (Ill.) -- History -- 19th century; Bombs (explosive weapons); Broadsides (notices); Ephemera (general object genre); Photographs; Editors; Judges; Lawyers; Engel, George, d. 1887 -- Portraits; Fielden, Samuel, 1847- -- Portraits; Fischer, Adolph, 1858-1887; Furthmann, Edmund; Gary, Joseph E. (Joseph Easton), 1821-1906; Grinnell, Julius S. (Julius Sprague), 1842-1898; Ingham, George C., 1851-1891; Lingg, Louis, d. 1887 -- Portraits; Most, Johann Joseph, 1846-1906; Neebe, Oscar W., 1850- -- Portraits; Parsons, Albert Richard, 1848-1887 -- Portraits; Parsons, Lucy E. (Lucy Eldine), 1853-1942; Schwab, Michael, 1853- -- Portraits; Spies, August Vincent Theodore, 1855-1887; International Working People's Association
- Haymarket Trial Evidence, Dates 1883-86; Series I; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I consists of material collected as evidence for the Haymarket trial, including correspondence of the defendants; drafts, proofs, and printed versions of the IWPA publications they edited; other printed material such as broadsides advertising meetings; and other physical evidence including fragments of the Haymarket bomb.
  Three fragments of the bomb are present in the collection. Two were removed from the body of Mathias J. Degan, for whose murder the eight anarchists were tried, and one from a wound in the foot of another officer. These were introduced in court during testimony of doctors who treated the officers and of metallurgists who examined the composition of the fragments in comparison to other bombs known to have been made by Louis Lingg.
  Trial evidence is arranged by exhibit number for those items in the collection for which matches could be made to the exhibits listed in the trial transcript filed with the Illinois Supreme Court, 1886 Nov 26 (consulted by the archivist via the Chicago Historical Society Haymarket Affair Digital Collection, www.chicagohistory.org/hadc/hadctoc.htm). Other items introduced in court during testimony were not given exhibit numbers, and several of these are present in the collection. In addition to the bomb fragments, these include letters from Johann Most and Michael Malkow, confiscated with other papers from August Spies's desk at the Arbeiter-Zeitung office, and a fulminating cap that was found on Adolph Fischer at his arrest. Additional papers from the Arbeiter-Zeitung office and several socialist and anarchist newspapers collected by the prosecution seem not to have been used in the trial.
  Much of the evidence is in German. In most cases, English translations and/or the printed newspaper copy seem to have been officially entered into evidence. The original German-language manuscripts were brought before witnesses for the purpose of identifying handwriting, and many are annotated as trial exhibits by court employee J. M. Purcell, but they remained in the State's Attorney's possession. A few items apparently entered into the evidence examined by the jury are present, including the "Revenge! / Rache!" broadside (People's Exhibit 6).
  Manuscript drafts taken from the Arbeiter-Zeitung office are for the most part incomplete; for many only small fragments are present. While some pages seem to have been torn into pieces by the compositors in the normal course of their work, others were clearly cut at some point after they were seized by the state. For example, page ten of the draft identified as People's Exhibit 73 was cut after it was marked by the court. Likewise, while many of the annotations on the manuscripts appear to have been made by the staff of the newspaper, others were made by the State's Attorney's office, marking passages to be translated or quoted as evidence, or indicating the date of publication.
  Correspondence to August Spies and others at the Arbeiter-Zeitung office documents to some extent the editorial work of the press, as well as interaction between the Chicago IWPA and IWPA groups in other cities, particulary New York, where Die Freiheit, a sister paper, was edited by Johann Most.
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into four subseries: Bomb Fragments, Numbered Exhibits, Other Papers Seized from Defendants, and Newspapers.
  - BOMB FRAGMENTS
    - "Part of Bomb taken from Degan's Body," two fragments, [1886] (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Accompanied by two envelopes of the State's Attorney's office, inscribed, and by fragment of German-language newspaper in which bomb fragments were wrapped
    - "Piece of metal removed from Police Officer Barbour's heel [...]," one fragment, 1886 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Accompanied by envelope inscribed by Dr. F. H. Newman, and by note in JSG's hand, "Carl Frye"
  - NUMBERED EXHIBITS
    - People's Exhibit 5. "Attention Workingmen! Great Mass-Meeting To-Night [...]," broadside, [1886 May 4] (Box 1, Folder 3)
      In English and German; one copy each of first and second edition (with and without phrase "Workingmen Arm Yourselves and Appear in Full Force"); first edition inscribed "Fischer"
    - People's Exhibit 6. "Revenge! Workingmen, To Arms!!! / Rache! Rache! Abeiter, zu den Waffen!", broadside, [1886 May 3]
      In English and German; signed on verso by police officer J. [James] H. Bonfield, defense attorneys Salomon and Zeisler, and the court; accompanied by note by F. B. Adams, Jr., 1953 Jan 7
    - People's Exhibit 18. "To Tramps, The Unemployed, the Disinherited, and Miserable," broadside, 1884 Oct 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Article by Lucy Parsons reprinted from The Alarm; the newspaper, not this broadside, was entered into evidence; accompanied by envelope of State's Attorney's office inscribed "Anarchist -Scraps-"
    - People's Exhibit 32. Anarchist, Organ der Autonomen Gruppen der I. A. A., Chicago, 1886 Jan 1
      Annotated by the court, initialled by Salomon and Zeisler
    - People's Exhibit 45. The Alarm, Chicago, 1885 Jun 27
    - People's Exhibit 61A. Schwab, Michael, "Heute Abend ist auf dem Heumarkt [...]," holograph draft, [1886 May 3]
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Box 1, folder 6
    - People's Exhibit 63. Spies, August, "Blut. Die Blei und Pulver Kur [...]," holograph draft, [1886 May 3] (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Final page differs from published text
    - People's Exhibits 64-65. Schwab, Michael, "Editorielle Notizen," holograph draft, [1886 May 3] (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Appeared in Arbeiter-Zeitung 1886 May 4; pages 1-2 are People's Exhibits 64-65; lower half of page 2 is People's Exhibit 61A; page 3 is People's Exhibit 67; pages 7-8 are People's Exhibit 66; part of page 4 and pages 5-6 missing
    - People's Exhibit 66. Schwab, Michael, "Das Zeughaus an Michigan See [...]," holograph draft, [1886 May 3]
    - People's Exhibit 67. Schwab, Michael, "Dass sonst so ruhiges Milwaukee [...]," holograph draft, [1886 May 3]
    - People's Exhibit 68. Spies, August, "Ein heisser Kampf," holograph draft, fragment, [1886 May 2] (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Part of page 3 and pages following page 4 missing; annotated by court verso p. 4
    - People's Exhibit 69. Schwab, Michael, "Waffen sind in unserer Zeit [...]," holograph draft, fragment, [1886 Apr 27] (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Annotated by court on verso
    - People's Exhibit 70. Schwab, Michael, "Wenn die gesetzlichen Mittel der Diebe [...]," holograph draft, [1886 Apr 28] (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Part of "Editorielle Notizen" for 1886 Apr 29; annotated by court on verso
      See also: galley proofs, Box bsd, folder 109
    - People's Exhibit 72. Spies, August, "Die ersten 24 Stunden das Kampfes sind über [...]," holograph draft, fragment, [1886 May 2] (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Pages 3-5 only; annotated by court on verso
    - People's Exhibit 73. Schwab, Michael, "Editorielles. Blut ist geflossen [...]," holograph draft, [1886 May 3] (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Missing end; annotated by court verso p. 10
    - People's Exhibit 74. Spies, August, "Edit. Ein Ausbruch wurde heute Morgen [...]," holograph draft, [1886 May 4] (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Annotated by court verso p. 2
    - People's Exhibit 89. Schwab, Michael, "[...] stehen Gewehre und kugelspritzen. [...]," holograph draft, fragment, 1886 Apr [20?] (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Final page only
    - Defense Exhibit 2. "Victor Hugo! His Two Messages: One to the Rich, the Other to the Poor," leaflet, [ca. 1885] (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Published by IWPA; reprint from The Alarm; the newspaper, not the leaflet, was entered into evidence
  - OTHER PAPERS SEIZED FROM DEFENDANTS
    In German unless otherwise noted
    - Drafts from Arbeiter-Zeitung Office
      - August Spies
        - "Zu Central Labor Union," draft fragment, holograph, [1886] (Box 2, Folder 15)
          Report on meeting and meeting notice
        - "Die Deutsche Sattler Union und die 'Ritter der Arbeit'," holograph draft, [1886] (Box 2, Folder 16)
          First page only; accompanied by carbon copy of earlier report on founding of the union, and meeting notice; also accompanied by FBA catalog card
        - "Die Gerber," holograph draft, [1886] (Box 2, Folder 17)
          Report on meeting of tanners union; accompanied by FBA catalog card
        - "Zu [?]. Die Lumberyard-Arbeiter- Union [...]," meeting reports, holograph drafts, [1886] (Box 2, Folder 18)
          Accompanied by typescript transcript, corrected
        - "Für Arb. & Angel. Die Ordnung [...]," holograph draft, fragment, [1886] (Box 2, Folder 19)
          First page only